Guide to the Oregonian photographs collection circa 1850-1984
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
- Oversize A, 1916-1984; Series I
  - Boats and Other Watercraft (5) (Box-folder 145/17)
  - Boeing Corp.; Bonneville Power Administration; Boise-Cascade Corp.; Books; Boots; Bottles; Buddhists (Box-folder 146/1)
  - Building Collapse; Building Demolition; Bus Drivers; Bus Shelters; Bus Terminals (Box-folder 146/2)
  - Cabins; Calendars; Campgrounds; Cans; Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (1) (Box-folder 146/3)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (2) (Box-folder 146/4)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (3) (Box-folder 146/5)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (4) (Box-folder 146/6)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (5) (Box-folder 146/7)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (6) (Box-folder 146/8)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (7) (Box-folder 146/9)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles (8) (Box-folder 146/10)
  - Carousels; Census; Child Abandonment; Child Care; Child Development (Box-folder 146/11)
  - Children (1) (Box-folder 146/12)
  - Children (2); China Dishes (Box-folder 146/13)
  - Christmas Celebrations; Christmas Decorations; Christmas Lights; Christmas Pageants (Box-folder 146/14)
  - Christmas Shopping; Christmas Trees (Box-folder 146/15)
  - Church Attendance Graph (1978); Cigarettes (Box-folder 147/1)
  - Clocks; Clouds; Coins (Box-folder 147/2)
  - Collectors and Collections; Communes; Computers (Box-folder 147/3)
  - Condominiums; Construction; Cornerstones; Cosmetics; Cotillion Balls; Covered Bridges (Box-folder 147/4)
  - Cowboys; Crane Accidents; Cranes; Credit Cards; Daylight; Daylight Savings Time; Deaf People (Box-folder 147/5)
  - Delivery Services; Demonstrations; Disaster Drills; Dog Shows (Box-folder 147/6)
  - Drownings; Earth Movers; Earthquakes; Earrings; Easter Eggs; Eclipses (Box-folder 147/7)
  - Education (1) (Box-folder 147/8)
  - Education (2) (Box-folder 147/9)
  - Elevators; Emergency Services; Employment; Energy (Box-folder 147/10)
  - Families; Fashion (1) (Box-folder 147/11)
  - Fashion (2); Fences; Fire Escapes (Box-folder 147/12)
  - Fires and Firefighting (1) (Box-folder 147/13)
  - Fires and Firefighting (2); Fireworks; Fish Ladders (Box-folder 147/14)
  - Fishing (1) (Box-folder 147/15)
  - Fishing (2) (Box-folder 147/16)
  - Fishing (3) (Box-folder 148/1)
  - Fishing (4) (Box-folder 148/2)
  - Flags; Flea Markets (Box-folder 148/3)
  - Flora and Fauna (1) (Box-folder 148/4)
  - Flora and Fauna (2) (Box-folder 148/5)
  - Flora and Fauna (3) (Box-folder 148/6)
  - Flora and Fauna (4) (Box-folder 148/7)
  - Flora and Fauna (5) (Box-folder 148/8)
  - Flora and Fauna (6) (Box-folder 148/9)
  - Flora and Fauna (7) (Box-folder 148/10)
  - Flora and Fauna (8) (Box-folder 148/11)
  - Flora and Fauna (9) (Box-folder 148/12)
  - Food and Beverage (1) (Box-folder 148/13)
  - Food and Beverage (2); Food Stamps (Box-folder 148/14)
  - Forestry (1) (Box-folder 148/15)
  - Forestry (2) (Box-folder 148/16)
  - Fundraising; Funerals; Gadgets; Gambling Raids (Box-folder 148/17)
  - Garage Sales; Garbage; Gems; Gold Mining (Box-folder 149/1)
  - Grandparents; Gravel Pits; Greenpeace Foundation; Guns; Hair; Hairstyles; Hazardous Materials (Box-folder 149/2)
  - Health and Medicine (1) (Box-folder 149/3)
  - Health and Medicine (2) (Box-folder 149/4)
  - Highway Construction; Highway Repairs; Highway Signs; Hitchhiking; Hoboes (Box-folder 149/5)
  - Home Building; Home Improvement and Remodeling; Home Shows and Tours; Hot Tubs (Box-folder 149/6)
    Includes some photographs of home construction that had originally been filed under "Housing."
  - House Moving; Houses and Housing; Houseboats; Income Tax (Box-folder 149/7)
  - Indians of North America (1) (Box-folder 149/8)
  - Indians of North America (2) (Box-folder 149/9)
  - Insulation; Iran Hostage Crisis (1980-1981); Jewish Holidays; Job Training; King Tutankhamen Exhibit (1978); Liberty Bell; Litter (Box-folder 149/10)
  - Magazines; Mail; Marijuana; Maypoles; Mentally Disabled People; Meter Maids (Box-folder 149/11)
  - Military (1) (Box-folder 149/12)
  - Military (2) (Box-folder 149/13)
  - Minor Emancipation; Mobile Homes; Models; Mountain Climbing Rescues; Music (1) (Box-folder 149/14)
    Models refers to fashion models. For toy and miniature models, see: Oversize A - Toys, Models and Other Merrymaking Devices.
  - Music (2) (Box-folder 149/15)
    Includes images of Chamber Music Northwest, the Forest Grove Gleemen, the Mt. Hood Jazz Festival, and the Portland Junior Symphony.
  - Performing Arts (1) (Box-folder 150/1)
  - Performing Arts (2) (Box-folder 150/2)
  - Performing Arts (3); Pesticides; Pharmaceutical Drug Price Chart (1972); Physically Disabled People (1) (Box-folder 150/3)
  - Physically Disabled People (2) (Box-folder 150/4)
  - Politics (Box-folder 150/5)
    Includes images of the Oregon State Legislature and a photograph of the 1978 Atiyeh-Straub debate.
  - Railroads; Religious Groups and Organizations; Roma People; Sacco and Vanzetti Trial (Box-folder 150/6)
    The photograph of Roma people had been originally filed under "Gyspsy."
  - Sports and Recreation (1) (Box-folder 150/7)
  - Sports and Recreation (2) (Box-folder 150/8)
  - Sports and Recreation (3) (Box-folder 150/9)
  - Sports and Recreation (4) (Box-folder 150/10)
  - Sports and Recreation (5) (Box-folder 150/11)
  - Sports and Recreation - Bicycling (1) (Box-folder 151/1)
  - Sports and Recreation - Bicycling (2) (Box-folder 151/2)
  - Sports and Recreation - Bicycling (3) (Box-folder 151/3)
  - Toys, Models and Other Merrymaking Devices (1) (Box-folder 151/4)
  - Toys, Models and Other Merrymaking Devices (2); Trailers (Box-folder 151/5)
  - Weather and Seasons (1) (Box-folder 151/6)
  - Weather and Seasons (2) (Box-folder 151/7)
  - Weather and Seasons (3) (Box-folder 151/8)
  - Weather and Seasons (4) (Box-folder 151/9)
  - Weather and Seasons (5); Weddings; Wireless Radios (Box-folder 151/10)
- Oversize B, 1880-1982; Series J
  Oversize images up to 19 by 25 inches.
  Many of the images are in multiple pieces adhered together and/or have labels taped to the image surface. Handle with care.
  - People (1) (Box-folder 152/1)
  - People (2) (Box-folder 152/2)
  - People - Kennedy, Robert F., 1968 (Box-folder 152/3)
  - People - Groups (Box-folder 152/4)
  - Oregon, Subseries 1
    - Alkali Lake; Ashland; Bagby Hot Springs; Beaverton; Bombings; Bridges (1) (Box-folder 152/5)
    - Bridges (2) (Box-folder 152/6)
    - Brookings; Bull Run Watershed; Camp Ky-O-Wa; Camp Menucha; Champoeg; Clackamas County; Clackamas County Fair (Box-folder 152/7)
      Includes a 1948 drawing of a proposed Champeog Memorial Museum.
    - Columbia River and Gorge; Corvallis - Hewlett-Packard Co.; Dams (Box-folder 152/8)
      Includes a photograph of the site for the proposed Umatilla Dam.
    - Bonneville Dam Site, 1933 (Box-folder 152/9)
    - Bonneville Dam and Aerial Tram Transparency (Box-folder 152/10)
      Undated ink drawing on transparent sheet showing proposed aerial tram with Bonneville Dam in the background. Kept separate for preservation purposes.
    - Deschutes Eiver Irrigation Project Map, 1938 January (Box-folder 152/11)
    - Deschutes River; Eastern Oregon; Ecola State Park; Eugene; Explosions; Fires; Florence; Forest Fires (Box-folder 152/12)
    - Fort Stevens; Gardiner; Garibaldi; Government Camp; Gresham; Highways (Box-folder 152/13)
    - Hillsboro; Mt. Hood; Mt. Hood National Forest; Hood River; Hood River Meadows; Hood River Valley; Huntington (Box-folder 152/14)
    - Jubitz Truck Stop; Kah-Nee-Tah; Klamath Falls; Lake Oswego; Lost Forest Dune Park (Box-folder 152/15)
    - Map of Arlington Relocation; Map of Oregon Coast Exploration, 1960; 1926 (Box-folder 153/1)
      Contains image of planned relocation of the town of Arlington to make way for the John Day Dam, and an atlas showing where on the Oregon Coast various European explorers made landfall.
    - Map of Our Lady of Guadalupe Monsatery (Box-folder 153/2)
      Kept separate for preservation reasons.
    - Milwaukie General Hospital, 1967 (Box-folder 153/3)
      Three drawings of floor plans.
    - Multnomah Falls; Nestucca Sand Spit State Park; Oregon City - Ainsworth Home; Salem; Steamboat Camp; Sun River; Three Sisters; Umpqua River; Wallowa Mountains; Wilsonville - Dammasch State Hospital (Box-folder 153/4)
    - Vanport Flood and Aftermath (1) (Box-folder 153/5)
    - Vanport Flood and Aftermath (2) (Box-folder 153/6)
  - Portland, Subseries 2
    - Addressograph-Multigraph Co.; Albertina Kerr Nursery; American Legion Convention (1970); American Plaza Apartments; B. P. John Furnitrue Co. (Box-folder 153/7)
    - Banks; Battleship Oregon Memorial Park; Bombings (Box-folder 153/8)
    - Boat Moorings Map, 1962 February 17 (Box-folder 153/9)
      Full-page map published in the Portland Reporter.
    - Bridges (Box-folder 153/10)
    - Bridges - Proprosed Morrison St. Bridge Approaches, 1954 (Box-folder 153/11)
    - Burke Concrete Accessories and Seaport Appliance; Capitol Center; Cascade Building; Cathedral Park; Catholic Sentinel Building; Central Plaza South; Chinatown Disrict; Christmas Celebrations; Churches and Other Houses of Worship (Box-folder 153/12)
    - City Dump; Civil Defense Evacuation Traffic Plan; Columbia Junior Hunt Club; Community Chest; Community Music Center; Condolea Condominiums; Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Convention (1948); Cudahy Co. (Box-folder 153/13)
    - Demonstrations; Disatster Drills; Earth Day Celebrations; Easter Celebrations; Eastside Esplanade; Electro Metalalloys; Excused Pupil Rate Chart (1971); Fair Northwest (Box-folder 153/14)
    - Fairytale Parade; Fires; Floods; Fountains (Box-folder 153/15)
    - Flood Levee Reapairs Map, 1954 (Box-folder 153/16)
    - "Front Street in 1906;" "Front Street Buildings" (Box-folder 154/1)
    - Galleria; General Motors Acceptance; George Sack Trial (1954); Girl Scouts; Glendoveer Golf Course; Graphic Arts Center; Highland Games (Box-folder 154/2)
    - Highways and Freeways (Box-folder 154/3)
    - Hillsdale Center; Hospitals and Clinics; Hydrogen Bomb Flooding Simulation; Irvington Tennis Club; Jantzen Beach Center; Japanese-American Conference (1960 September); Japanese Trade Fair (1954); Jenkins Home (Box-folder 154/4)
      Includes a photograph showing the estimated water level in Portland that would result if a hydrogen bomb destroyed the Grand Coulee Dam, and an image of the residence of Barbara Jenkins.
    - Junior Chamber of Commerce Convention (1967 June); Junior League; Kay Manufacturing Co.; Knapp Home; Libraries; Linnton Plywood Co.; Linnton Shopping Center; March of Dimes (Box-folder 154/5)
      Includes a photograph of Richard B. Knapp's residence.
    - Memorial Coliseum; Memorial Day Celebrations; Meriwether Country Club; Model Cities; Multnomah Civic Stadium; Multnomah County Commission; Multnomah County Courthouse; Multnomah County Department of Medical Services; Nationwide Insurance Co.; Navy Day (1946 October 25) (Box-folder 154/6)
    - Oregonian Building, circa 1955 (Box-folder 154/7)
    - Park Blocks; Police Department - Sunshine Division; Port of Portland Map; Portland Meadows; Portland Rose Festival (Box-folder 154/8)
    - Portland High School (Box-folder 154/9)
    - Public Market Building; Public Service Building; Rapid Car Wash, Inc.; Reser's Fine Foods; Sheraton Motor Inn; Sixth Avenue Hotel; Standard Plaza; State Finance Co.; Swan Island; Swan Island Airport; Texas Oil Co. (Box-folder 154/10)
    - Tri-Met (Box-folder 154/11)
      Contains bus route maps and conceptual art for a bus terminal.
    - United States Courthouse; Urban Renewal; Vaughn Street Park; Washington Park; Washington Park - Japanese Garden; Washington Park Zoo (Box-folder 154/12)
  - Washington State; Other US Locations - California; Abortion; "America" Photoseries (Box-folder 154/13)
    Includes 1 oversize image from the February 1971 "America" photo series.
  - Agriculture; Apprenticeships; Architectural Drawing of a Library (1981) (Box-folder 155/1)
    Includes a conceptual drawing for a planned library in an unnamed location.
  - Archaeology - Marmes Skeleton Skull, 1968 (Box-folder 155/2)
    Drawing of the skull parts found by Washington State University professor Roal Fryxwell at Marmes Rock Shelter, Washington.
  - Art; Asian-American People; Auctions; Aviation (Box-folder 155/3)
  - Babies; Bank Robberies; Boats and Other Watercraft; Boy Scouts (Box-folder 155/4)
  - Cars and Other Motor Vehicles; Children (Box-folder 155/5)
    Includes photographs of automobile wrecking yards and a diagram on how to turn potatoes into car fuel.
  - Christmas Decorations; Christmas Lights; Clouds; Collectors and Collections; Computers; Construction; Cranes; Dating; Deaf People; Dog Shows; Eclipses; Emotionally Disturbed Children; Evolutionary Chart (Box-folder 155/6)
  - Fashion; Fires and Firefighting; Fireworks; Fishing (Box-folder 155/7)
  - Flags; Flora and Fauna (Box-folder 155/8)
  - Food and Beverage; Forestry; Freighting Outfit Diagram (Box-folder 155/9)
    Includes a diagram of John Noble's horse-drawn freighting outfit.
  - Garbage; Glass Floats; Hairstyles; Health and Medicine - Alcoholism, Blood Donors; Highway Construction; Hispanic-American People; Houses and Housing; Houseboats (Box-folder 155/10)
  - Income Tax; Indian Thanksgiving Celebrations; Janitors; Junkyards; Landscaping; Liberty Bell; Mail; Mailboxes; Mentally Disabled People (Box-folder 156/1)
  - Military (Box-folder 156/2)
  - Military - World War II - Possible Routes of Invasion of the United States, 1940 August (Box-folder 156/3)
    Published in August 11, 1940 issue with headline, "Invasion: Threat or Bugaboo?"
  - Mobile Homes; Mothers; Music; Performing Arts; Politics (Box-folder 156/4)
  - "Pillars in the Sky" Production Shots, 1955 August (Box-folder 156/5)
    7 sheets of images taken during the production of the film "Pillars in the Sky."
  - Political Cartoons, 1880 (Box-folder 156/6)
    Contains Puck cartoons "The Hero of a Thousand Feeds," "Sanctus Roscoe-rus," "The New 'Rip' or 'Twenty-Five Years Asleep,'" "Let Us Have Peace, Now a President's Elected," and "A Pinaforic Suggestion"
  - Railroads; Sports and Recreation (Box-folder 156/7)
  - Toys, Models and Other Merrymaking Devices; Water Conservation District Maps; Weather and Seasons (Box-folder 156/8)
- Oversize, 1926-1976; Series K
  Images larger than 19 by 25 inches.
  - Fremont Bridge, 1973 November (Box-folder Folder 1)
  - Conceptual Drawins of Coos Bay, Cowlitz River, and Suislaw River Bridges (Box-folder Folder 2)
  - Conceptual Drawings of; Portland Bazaar, Beebe Co. Shop; Firestone Tire & Rubber Co. Distribution Center; Forest Hills County Club Addition; Fred Meyer Gateway Shopping Center Expansion Plan; Harbor Patrol Boat; Portland Labor Center; Lovejoy Medical Center (Box-folder Folder 3)
  - Conceptual Drawing of Marquam Bridge (Box-folder Folder 4)
    Also includes letter by Douglas Lynch of the Art Commission to Terry Schrunk concerning the bridge's design.
  - Conceptual Drawings of Proposals for New Sellwood Bridge, 1965 (Box-folder Folder 5)
    Contains drawings of three alternate bridge plans
  - Conceptual Drawings of Proposed Floating Bridge in Puget Sound, east end of Broadway Bridge, and Proposed Traffic Interchange between Harbor Drive and Steel Bridge (Box-folder Folder 6)
    Due to the size of one of the the images, these images are housed in two overlapping folders.
  - Conceptual Map of Bull Run Watershed (Box-folder Folder 7)
  - Composite Photograph of Oregon Legislature, 1973 (Box-folder Folder 8)
  - Lithia Park Memorial Rose Garden Map, 1958 (Box-folder Folder 9)
  - Map of George L. Baker's Subdivision at Seaside, 1926 August (Box-folder Folder 10)
  - Portrait of Unidentified Woman, circa 1950 (Box-folder Folder 11)
  - Tillamook Bay Jetty Project, circa 1930 (Box-folder Folder 12)
  - Vanport Post-Flood Panorama, 1948 July (Box-folder Folder 13)
    Due to the size of the image, it is housed in two overlapping folders.
  - Western Kraft Paper Co. Chip Pile, 1956 (Box-folder Folder 14)
- Written Materials, 1890-1972; Series L
  Written materials and ephemera that were found in the collection.
  - 4-H Club Member Poster (Box-folder 157/1)
  - 10th Avenue Building Brochure (Box-folder 157/2)
  - Ben Franklin Lock and Dam Brochure, 1968 (Box-folder 157/3)
  - Bonneville Power Administration Charts, 1956 (Box-folder 157/4)
  - Canton, China Essay, circa 1930 (Box-folder 157/5)
  - Clackamas County Bicentennial Historical Map, 1976 (Box-folder 157/6)
  - "The Coin Banks of the World" Article (Box-folder 157/7)
  - "Crime Prevention" Issue, 1949 (Box-folder 157/8)
  - Democratic National Convention Flyer, 1908 (Box-folder 157/9)
  - "Driving in the Golden Spike" (Box-folder 157/10)
    Contains booklet, and a letter from Northern Pacific Railway Advertising Department. See Subjects - Railroads - Construction and Last Spike Ceremonies for images referred to in letter.
  - First Congregational Church Centennial Brochue, 1951 (Box-folder 157/11)
  - Forestry and Lumber History Essay (Box-folder 157/12)
  - Frances Benjamin Johnston Article, 1930 (Box-folder 157/13)
  - Freight Car Construction Press Release, 1950 (Box-folder 157/14)
    See Subjects - Railroads - Freight Car Construction for images referred to in press release.
  - Goat Rocks Wild Area Brochure, 1964 (Box-folder 157/15)
  - Government Fish Study Article, 1929 (Box-folder 157/16)
  - Instructions and Warnings to Mt. St. Helens Climbers, 1955 (Box-folder 157/17)
  - Jacksonville Museum Brochure, 1959 (Box-folder 157/18)
  - Mr. and Mrs. D. B. Steinman Christmas Card, 1941 (Box-folder 157/19)
    Includes a color drawing of the St. Johns Bridge.
  - Oregonian Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 157/20)
    Primarily requests to other newspapers for photographs of columnists.
  - Pictorial News Annual Special Features, 1950 (Box-folder 158/1)
    See also: Subjects - "Disasters, 1900-1950;" Subjects - "Great Moments in History, 1900-1950."
  - Pioneer Memorial Unveiling Brochure, 1959 (Box-folder 158/2)
  - Press Release for Irving Penn's "Flowers", 1980 (Box-folder 158/3)
    See Subjects - Flora and Fauna - Flowers for associated photographs.
  - Script for Oregonian 75th Anniversary Program, 1925 December (Box-folder 158/3)
  - Solar Eclipse Brochure (Box-folder 158/4)
  - "Ten Outstanding Young Men" Press Kit, 1967 (Box-folder 158/5)
  - Text of Otto Kahn's Address "Mussolini and Italy" (Box-folder 158/6)
  - Tsar Alexander I Article, 1930 (Box-folder 158/7)
  - "West Shore" Illustrated Journa, 1890 (Box-folder 158/8)
  - Clippings (1) (Box-folder 158/9)
    Clippings folders contain newspaper articles from the 1920s and 1930s that either did not include images in the collection or were full-page stories. Clippings are wrapped in a piece of archival paper, on which the clippings' content matter is briefly noted; they are otherwise unordered.
  - Clippings (2) (Box-folder 158/10)
  - Clippings (3) (Box-folder 158/11)
  - Clippings (4) (Box-folder 159/1)
  - Clippings (5) (Box-folder 159/2)
  - Clippings (6) (Box-folder 159/3)
  - Clippings (7) (Box-folder 159/4)
  - Clippings (8) (Box-folder 159/5)
  - Clippings (9) (Box-folder 159/6)
  - Clippings (10) (Box-folder 159/7)
  - Clippings (11) (Box-folder 159/8)
  - Recap of Oregonian Housing Survey, 1951 (Box-folder 156/9)
    Printed on blueprint paper.
- Negatives, 1928-1957; Series M (Box-folder Box 160)
  Access to this series is restricted.
  Contains 45 images on 30 pieces of negative film. Matching prints or reference printouts filed in the collection.